<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1" xml:id="tinkar_model_concept_appenidix">
    <title>Tinkar Model Concepts (In Progress)</title>
    <para>&lt;&lt;IN PROGRESS; DRAFT >> </para>
    <para>The Tinkar core architecture is designed to be extremely flexible. This flexibility
        supports the ability to assert relationships among diverse terminologies and to support
        change in the design of those terminologies. However, it means that there may be more than
        one way to support any specific requirement. </para>
    <para>We propose the following members of the Tinkar Model Concepts (a.k.a. infrastructure
        concepts). </para>
    <para>Below is an example of a subset of Tinkar Model Concepts. The full list and definitions of
        the core Tinkar Model Concepts is in progress and will be completed by the ballot submission
        deadline.</para>
    <para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>User: An agent that may be responsible for authoring a change.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Content license: Official permision to use intellectual property.<itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Apache 2 license: A permissive free software license written by
                                the Apache Software Foundation.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para> CC_BY_LICENSE: A license used when an author wants to give other
                                people the right to share, use, and build upon a work that they have
                                created.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Copyright: A type of intellectual property that gives its owner the exclusive
                    right to make copies of a creative work, usually for a limited time.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Description semantic set: A semantic set specifying how a concept is
                    described.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Dependency management semantic set: A semantic set specifying how modules
                    depend on one another.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> Dialect semantic set: A semantic set enumerating descriptions in a specified
                    dialect.</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> GB English dialect: A semantic set enumerating descriptions in GB
                            English.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> US English dialect: A semantic set enumerating descriptions in US
                            English.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para> US Nursing dialect: A semantic set enumerating descriptions in US
                            English tailored for nursing use.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
</appendix>
