<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<glossary xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:id="gloss">
    <title>Glossary</title>
    <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>Term</entry>
                    <entry>Definition</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Capability maturity model</entry>
                    <entry>A development model that can be viewed as a set of structured levels that
                        describe how well the behaviors, practices and processes of an organization
                        can reliably and sustainably produce required outcomes. There are five
                        levels defined along the continuum of the capability maturity model; the
                        model provides a theoretical continuum along which process maturity can be
                        developed incrementally from one level to the next.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Foundation Layer of Knowledge Architecture </para>
                        <para> </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>The Foundation layer of the Knowledge Architecture provides the common
                        elements of interoperability such as object identity, versioning,
                        modularity, and knowledge representation. It includes (a) the foundation and
                        building blocks of the common model; (b) how the repeatable transformation
                        process of disparate standards into the common model promotes
                        interoperability with other environments; and (c) how the modules of the
                        architecture are tightly version controlled over time.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Logical Model</para>
                        <para> </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>A model expressed independently of a particular implementation
                        technology.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Komet (Knowledge Management Environement)</entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Komet is an example implementation of the Tinkar standard,  and how
                            various terminologies, such as SNOMED, LOINC, RxNorm, and HL7
                            terminologies shall be reproducibly represented. Using the Komet browser
                            we can view the search concepts, view the concept details, and navigate
                            hierarchies among many other functions that are outside the scope of
                            this ballot.</para>
                    </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Terminology Knowledge Layer of Knowledge Architecture </para>
                        <para> </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>The Terminology Knowledge layer is responsible for structured sets of
                        medical terms and codes that define concepts of interest, including
                        descriptions, dialects, language, and semantic hierarchy. SNOMED CT, LOINC,
                        and RxNorm are part of this layer.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Tinkar Reference Model</para>
                        <para> </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>The Tinkar Reference Model, is a logical model that describes the
                        standardized model for terminology and change management.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>Separation of Concerns</entry>
                    <entry>A design principle that allows a complete system to be subdivided into
                        distinct sections or components with well-defined functionality and
                        dependencies. If successful, this approach allows individual sections to be
                        able to be reused, as well as worked on and updated independently to address
                        new requirements and use cases.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>
                        <para>Solor</para>
                        <para> </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>A project sponsored by the Department of Veterans Affairs and Logica
                        Health (formerly HSPC) that represents and brings together different
                        terminology standards by using a single model that can encompass any
                        customized content. Solor allows informaticists and developers to convert
                        user-supplied terminologies into a single model using open source software
                        to produce Solor content. For more information please see solor.io.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>UML (Unified Modeling Language)</entry>
                    <entry>Unified Modeling Language is an Object Management Group (OMG)
                        specification defining a graphical language for visualizing, specifying,
                        constructing, and documenting the artifacts of distributed object
                        systems.</entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    
    
</glossary>
