<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="../../../docbook-customization/src/docbkx-stylesheet/common/komet.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>Over the past decades, biomedical terminologies have increasingly been recognized as key
    resources for knowledge management, data integration, and decision support (<link
      xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6115234/">1</link> – REF).
    Acceleration and development of Electronic Health Record (EHR) systems has precipitated the
    emergence of “standard terminologies” and their widespread adoption in the clinical community.
    These include Systematized Nomenclature of Medicine Clinical Terms (SNOMED CT), the Logical
    Observation Identifiers, Names, and Codes (LOINC®) and RxNorm. The availability of these
    clinical terminologies through the unified terminology services of FHIR is facilitating their
    usage in support of interoperability in healthcare. </para>
  <para>Interoperability requires standardized semantics based on reference terminology provided by
    standards development organizations, professional organization, or government agencies. These
    organizations publish their content with the intention of licensing it to health IT vendors,
    providers, and research organizations. In the U.S., the core clinical reference terminology is
    based on SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm. Healthcare organizations have to adopt and integrate
    subsets or modules of various reference terminology and manage references, dependencies,
    versions, and releases. It is important for the integrity of medical records that concepts and
    value sets change history can be managed and tracked to allow the exchange of either current or
    retrospective health records. Therefore, enterprise terminology requires integrated terminology
    using a common representation and management.</para>
  <para>Despite the need to use standard terminologies in a highly integrated way, there is no
    standard representation across SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm, etc. Some partnerships have been
    created among development teams to facilitate interoperability and minimize duplication of
    effort. Further integration has been proposed but will require additional resources to bring
    these terminologies closer together. However, while this evolution leads to greater
    compatibility and interoperability, integration of SNOMED CT, LOINC, and RxNorm in non-trivial
    as these terminologies have different semantics models, and use different formalisms and tools
    for their representation, have separate release cycles, and different versioning mechanisms.
    There is little recognition that terminology standards are not standardized at the exchange
    level. Even HL7 has three dissimilar ways to represent concepts, value sets, and code systems. </para>
  <para>In this document, we focus on the need for – and logical specification of – a Terminology
    Knowledge Architecture (Tinkar). Tinkar is intended to provide an architecture that delivers
    integrated terminology to the enterprise and its information systems, that addresses the
    differences in management and structure across reference terminology and with local concepts and
    code lists/value sets. The Tinkar Reference Model, is a logical model that describes the
    standardized model for terminology and change management. </para>
  <para>A Tinkar Specification could provide a single representation for all terminologies required
    in the U.S. that meet the following criteria for managing change from the capability maturity
    model (REF needed): </para>
  <para><emphasis role="bold">Initial</emphasis> – Tinkar aims to reduce and eliminate challenges
    with management of changes to terminology being unpredictable, poorly controlled, and
    reactive</para>
  <para><emphasis role="bold">Repeatable</emphasis> – Tinkar provides the foundation for robust
    configuration management and quality assurance for terminologies</para>
  <para><emphasis role="bold">Defined</emphasis> – Tinkar allowing terminologies to have
    standardized update and extension process</para>
  <para><emphasis role="bold">Managed</emphasis> – Tinkar represenents updates and changes to
    terminologies so that the changes can be measured and controlled</para>
  <para><emphasis role="bold">Optimizing</emphasis> – Tinkar aims to allow multiple stakeholders to
    apply and retrieve changes to shared terminology content with equivalent and harmonized
    results</para>
  <para>Tinkar aims to adhere to the following statement from a publication about developments in
    clinical terminologies in the 2018 Yearbook of Medical Informatics (<link
      xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6115234/">2</link> --REF): “The
    benefits of the integrated terminologies in terms of homogenous semantics and inherent
    interoperability should, however, outweigh the complexity added to the system.” This
    specification provides the foundation of a knowledge architecture that is intended to integrate
    reference terminology from distributors (e.g. SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm) with local concepts in
    order to support interoperable information semantics across the enterprise. </para>
  <section>
    <title>Motivation: Why Tinkar?</title>
    <para>Information systems that are used across the healthcare enterprise record and manage
      clinical data using clinical statements and clinical terminologies in non standardized ways.
      Interoperability specifications aim to require terminology bindings to concepts, code systems,
      and reusable value sets. Currently, we see variation in clinical data exchange across the
      enterprise, as current payloads and clinical statements use inconsistent and highly variable
      enterprise terminologies. The management of the concepts, code systems, and value sets is
      non-trivial, as developers, implementers, and end users are forced to manage “unnecessary
      complexity”. For example:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Representation of medications: RxNorm codes overlap with CVX codes. Investigational
          vaccines from FDA are not represented in either RxNorm or CVX or SNOMED</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>HL7 gender codes, maybe COVID-19 rather than gender</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>As a result of these complexities, there are many ways to say the same thing using
      standard terminologies and standard formats. The Institute of Medicine report <emphasis
        role="italic">Health IT and Patient Safety: Building Safer Systems for Better
        Care</emphasis> highlighted the unintended consequences of health IT-induced harm that can
      result in serious injury and death due to dosing errors, failing to detect serious illnesses,
      and delaying treatment due to poor human-computer interactions, confusing clinical
      terminology, or unreliable data quality ([Institute of Medicine (2012). <emphasis
        role="italic">Health IT and Patient Safety. Building Safer Systems for Better
        Care</emphasis>. Washington, DC: National Academies Press] --REF ). Despite the widespread
      understanding of the importance of the quality of clinical data, there is currently a lack of
      integration and management of clinical terminologies across the healthcare enterprise. </para>
    <para> Tinkar intends to integrate clinical terminology and local concepts in order to support
      interoperable information and increased data quality for clinical information. Quality
      clinical data enables healthcare systems across the enterprise to enhance quality of care
      across all medical facilities, conduct robust and meaningful data analysis, and increase
      overall interoperability:</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Improved Patient Outcomes</emphasis></para>
    <para>Quality clinical data enables healthcare providers to enhance quality of care across all
      medical facilities, conduct robust and meaningful data analysis, and increase overall
      interoperability</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Meaningful Data Analysis </emphasis></para>
    <para>Medical facilities will be able to easily query specific health factors to gain necessary
      insights, draw conclusions, and make recommendations based on patient data</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Increased Interoperability</emphasis></para>
    <para>Health IT will have more interoperable capabilities, opening the door for future
      opportunities to integrate patient data with other agencies, community partners, and the
      private sector</para>
    <section>
      <title>The Problem Tinkar Addresses </title>
      <para>The following 3 high level potential deficiencies related to preventable harm that
        Tinkar aims to address related to poorly integrated terminology and inefficient change
        management : </para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Inability to recognize equivalence </emphasis></para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Difficulty with determining that codes/terms using standard terminologies from
            disparate health IT systems represent a common clinical idea/concept (e.g., “COVID-19
            negative test result”. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Inability to represent a pertinent phenomenon</emphasis></para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A new set of local terminology may be managed with value sets and concept gaps
            addressed in quick iterations (e.g., COVID-19 laboratory test results). </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Flawed information</emphasis></para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Incorrect usage or representation of clinical ideas/concepts from standard
            terminologies due to a lack of harmonization and multiple representations that currently
            exist (e.g., an incorrectly coded COVID-19 test result) </para>
          <para><emphasis role="underline">Consider the following examples of things that have gone
              wrong: (</emphasis><link
              xlink:href="https://www.systmoneusergroup.co.uk/qrisk2-update/"
              >https://www.systmoneusergroup.co.uk/qrisk2-update/</link>; <link
              xlink:href="https://www.bmj.com/content/353/bmj.i2742"
              >https://www.bmj.com/content/353/bmj.i2742</link>; <link
              xlink:href="https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mhra-information-on-tpp-and-qrisk2"
              >https://www.gov.uk/government/news/mhra-information-on-tpp-and-qrisk2</link>; <link
              xlink:href="https://www.healthcareitnews.com/news/clinical-decision-support-malfunctions-are-widespread-and-persistent-amia-says"
              >https://www.healthcareitnews.com/news/clinical-decision-support-malfunctions-are-widespread-and-persistent-amia-says</link><emphasis
              role="underline">) – REF</emphasis></para>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Computer error may have led to incorrect prescribing of
              statins to thousands of patients</emphasis></para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Thousands of patients in England may have been incorrectly prescribed or taken
                off statins because of a major IT glitch. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Underlying cause: code mapping errors, brittle means for determining
                equivalence</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Alert for monitoring thyroid function when taking Amiodarone
              stopped working</emphasis></para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Amiodarone is associated with several side effects, including thyroid
                dysfunction, which is due to amiodarone's high iodine content and its direct toxic
                effect on the thyroid</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Underlying cause: the identifier for the drug amiodarone was changed in another
                system, brittle means for determining equivalence</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">62% of CDS malfunctions were attributable to changes in
              underlying codes or data fields</emphasis></para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Change is a constant feature of providing healthcare </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Underlying cause: poorly managed change</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>Tinkar addresses challenges/problems from these implementation examples:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Challenge: Brittle terminology integration frequently breaks across
                systems</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>TInkar Solution: Standardize (and facilitate sharing) of terminology
                    representation across systems</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Challenge: Management of change over time</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Tinkar Solution: Consistent representation and configuration
                    management</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Challenge: SNOMED CT’s proprietary aspects prevents use as a common format for
                LOINC and similar</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Tinkar Solution: Build on existing SNOMED CT foundation, rather than
                    reinvent, using an open-source initiative approved permissive licenses (i.e.,
                    Apache 2)</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>About Tinkar</title>
    <para>Tinkar provides the foundation of a knowledge architecture that is intended to integrate
      reference terminology from distributors (e.g. SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm) with local concepts in
      order to support interoperable information semantics across the enterprise.</para>
    <para>This specification introduces an agile approach to terminology design and formatting that
      promotes the use of self-describing data. It is a shift from hard-coded models that have been
      favored due to their prescriptive nature but have shown limited flexibility and extensibility.
      Like FHIR, this specification places the focus on a self-describing, extensible approach to
      representing terminology. Therefore, Tinkar aims to be both self-describing and completely
      machine processed:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Self-describing in a machine-readable representation of terminology such that if an
          application can process the metadata, it should be able to import the content/concepts and
          present make it available to enterprise applications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The machine-readable terminology could to generate human-readable documentation, so
          that business analysts, developers can understand and apply it correctly.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <section>
      <title>Tinkar Objectives and Purpose – Manage Terminology and Change Better</title>
      <para>This specification is describing the requirements and characteristics of systems require
        to manage terminology produced by a variety of organization across a healthcare enterprise.
        This foundation must allow enterprise to extend terminology standards and implement
        extensions in a timely fashion.</para>
      <para>This specification is intended to support healthcare organizations standard terminology
        modules, value sets, and coding systems as well as local terms and equivalence
        mappings.</para>
      <para>A standard-based Terminology Knowledge Architecture (TINKAR) specification would be
        necessary to support the operation of a variety of systems intended to deliver knowledge
        management for terminology to vendors, provider, and even standards-development
        organizations like HL7. </para>
      <para>Previous efforts have attempted to create a common set of terminology capabilities and
        services by specifying a single pre-defined structure for managing terminology.
        Unfortunately, a hardwired structure that works for one standard may not work for another.
        The ability of to integrate content across terminology standards is a barrier to
        implementing services and modules that can deliver integrated concepts, code lists, and
        value sets required by enterprise systems for treatment, research, business process
        automation, quality measures, and outcome analysis. </para>
      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Clinical applications require integrated terminology to create interoperable
              clinical statements organized into messages, documents, or resources.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Data analysis and research require integrated terminology to analyze aggregated
              information. Interoperability, clinical decision support, or other types of automation
              require common semantics based on a set of integrated models across reference
              standards (e.g. SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm, etc)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>Tinkar is intended to provide an architecture that delivers integrated
        terminology to the enterprise and its information systems, that addresses the differences in
        management and structure across reference terminology and with local concepts and code
        lists/value sets. </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Related Efforts</title>
    <para>Previous efforts have attempted to create a common set of terminology capabilities and
      services by specifying a single pre-defined structure for managing terminology. Unfortunately,
      a hardwired structure that works for one standard may not work for another. The ability of to
      integrate content across terminology standards is a barrier to implementing services and
      modules that can deliver integrated concepts, code lists, and value sets required by
      enterprise systems for treatment, research, business process automation, quality measures, and
      outcome analysis. </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Clinical applications require integrated terminology to create interoperable clinical
          statements organized into messages, documents, or resources.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Data analysis and research require integrated terminology to analyze aggregated
          information. Interoperability, clinical decision support, or other types of automation
          require common semantics based on a set of integrated models across reference standards
          (e.g. SNOMED CT, LOINC, RxNorm, etc)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Tinkar is intended to provide an architecture that delivers integrated terminology to the
      enterprise and its information systems, that addresses the differences in management and
      structure across reference terminology and with local concepts and code lists/value sets. </para>
    <para>In a subsequent chapter &lt;insert link>, we include a more details gap analysis between
      Tinkar and other models such as CTS2, EVS, etc. ...</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Benefits of Self-Describing Architecture</title>
    <para>Tinkar aims to be both self-describing and completely machine processed. Key advantages of
      a self-describing architecture (or metadata driven architecture) include the following details
        (<link xlink:href="https://www.claysys.com/blog/metadata-driven-application-development/"/>
      – REF): </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Changes can be reviewed immediately</emphasis> – every action or
      change by end users can be immediately previewed or tested, without needing any compilation or
      deployment process. And the review can also be done before saving or publishing the changes,
      which makes it an interactive development environment, for designers to create functionality
      in an iterative manner.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Version Control with easy rollback</emphasis> - Since every
      published artifact for the web application being designed in a metadata file, every time any
      changes are made, the historic versions of the metadata files are maintained. This enables
      easy version control and rollback when necessary. What this mean is that every time a change
      is made to a Form or any artifact of an application, the prior version that existed is
      archived. So as and when you need to rollback to the prior version, it can be achieved through
      a single click of a button.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Any data source can be added </emphasis>– A self-describing
      architecture facilitates the ability for multiple types of terminology data sources to be
      connected to the system.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Define granular coordinates and configuration management</emphasis>
      – The functionality for defining granular user defined settings and controls for granular
      elements of clinical terminology management are supported. This includes
      Create/Read/Update/Delete (CRUD) settings, as well as management of individual elements like
      fields or other controls. </para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Faster extensions and updates – </emphasis>A benefit of a
      self-describing architecture is that it can abstract away a lot of the deep internal plumbing
      complexities that makes development of standard terminologies complicated. This approach can
      improve processes around updates to terminology. </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>About this Document</title>
    <para>This document describes how information systems can improve encoded clinical data with
      managing terminology and changes to terminology using a standardized model. </para>
    <para>In the following chapter we enumerate business requirements for Tinkar followed by Chapter
      X containing the Tinkar Reference Model and illustrative examples of terminology content
      represented by Tinkar. Subsequently, we present a reference implementation of Tinkar to
      demonstrate Tinkar in action. Finally, we discuss implications of TInkar on data quality,
      clinical decision support and patient safety and outcomes. </para>
    <note>
      <para>(Placeholder - NEED TO UPDATE)</para>
      <para>Being on the right side of IP” – language to refer to the fact that different sources
        have different requirements and we want to help meet end users needs – limit to how Tinkar
        could help navigating/managing</para>
    </note>
  </section>
</chapter>
